If you're building Rails applications
and you want to charge customers like a
SAS product, then you'll need to
implement a billing system. And if
you've ever done that before, you know
that there are so many moving parts.
There's a lot of billing code that goes
into building a robust SAS billing
system in a Rails app. And that's why I
built instrumental commerce. It is my
complete SAS billing system and Stripe
integration that I implement on every
one of my Rails applications that I
build. and it's included in instrumental
components. So, in this video, I want to
show you all aspects of instrumental
commerce. I'll show you a demo from the
checkout flow to the admin panel and
everything. Then, we'll tear it all down
and I'll show you how you can build it
in your Rails applications in literally
just a couple of commands in just a few
minutes. Now, there's a lot here because
when it comes to a SAS billing system,
there are so many essential components
and that's why it is so timeconuming and
so complex to actually implement all of
these tablestakes features that almost
every SAS application actually needs
when it comes to billing customers and
giving customers management over their
subscriptions and then implementing it
all in your Rails application. So, um,
with instrumental commerce, um, it
includes everything that I always want
to, uh, to build into my Rails apps.
Starting with a deep stripe
integrations, that that's how we can
process our payments. We want to give
users an easy way to select a plan, like
a pricing table. We're going to have an
optimized checkout flow. Um, of course,
we're going to be selling subscriptions
as well as one-time products. We want to
be able to handle coupons with
promotional codes and some smart logic
in the checkout flow for handling
coupons. Of course, we need to give
customers their own billing portal to uh
see the status of their subscription and
manage their payment methods. Now, when
you're dealing with subscriptions, of
course, and SAS businesses, you there
also needs to be a cancellation flow.
So, when customers need to cancel their
subscription, we also want to ask them
for a reason and they'll fill out a form
for that. Now, this is one of the most
important pieces and it goes under the
radar with SAS billing systems and
that's what's known as dunning. So, when
customers are subscribed and they're
paying month after month, but then their
credit cards fail, that results in
subscriptions becoming past due. Now, if
you don't have a dunning system in
place, then it's very easy for a SAS
business to leak revenue because of
these subscriptions that become past due
over time without a system to resolve
those. So that's what Dunning does. It
it builds in a system to notify
customers when their subscription
payments fail and give them an easy
frictionfree way to go in and resolve
their own payments so that you can
recover that subscription revenue.
Extremely important. Of course, there
needs to be an admin panel where you
manage your products as well as your
customer activity and accounts and
notifications throughout this whole
system. So, as you can see just in the
to-do list of building a uh a robust SAS
billing system, there is a lot here. So,
let's start with a quick demo to show
you uh what it actually looks like in an
implemented app and then we'll tear it
all down and I'll show you exactly how
to build all this. So, let's start from
the front end for what the customer
actually sees. So, we'll begin here.
This is the plan selection page. All of
this comes with instrumental commerce
right out of the box. So you'll get a
plans page where you can um manage you
know multiple plans and it has a monthly
or yearly toggle switch. This is a very
common pattern with SAS pricing pages.
In this case we're just you know selling
two plans. You can have more than that
of course. Um we've got a starter plan
and a pro plan. And then we're listing
out benefits with check marks and each
of these has a little tool tip. Again
these are very common patterns when it
comes to pricing pages for SAS. Um these
are the buttons that will lead to the
checkout. Below that we uh have the uh
FAQ component and that in itself is
another component that's included with
instrumental components. So commerce you
know pulls in many different components
like our buttons component, our tool
tips component um you know selections
like this. Okay. So the user is looking
at their their plan selection page and
they can go through and select a plan.
So, let's go with uh the starter plan,
$29 a month, and they'll choose that.
And then this takes the user into the
checkout flow. Again, this whole view
and user experience is included in
Instrumental Commerce. The first step of
the checkout is to identify the user.
So, they need to either register if
they're a totally new user or if they
are a returning user, they can click
this and it will um switch to a login
view. You'll notice here on the right,
we're actually showing the user which
product they're about to purchase. Um
what the price of the product is. In
this case, it is a subscription with a
trial. So, it'll tell them exactly when
their trial will expire. So, we're
giving them th those purchase details
here on the right. Of course, with
instrumental and all the layouts and
everything, you can, you know, customize
all the design and look and feel and the
branding. Um now all of this of course
is uh you know mobile optimized and it
is also dark mode friendly. So that's
that's the case with everything in
instrumental and okay so uh we're going
to start by registering as a totally new
user. Again this whole view is like
public um you know because you you'll be
promoting it to like public facing uh
visitors on your website. Okay. So I'm
just going to enter my email address and
create a password. And then that takes
me into the next step which is uh
collecting the payment details. Now this
whole form is powered by stripe payment
elements. This is a very robust API from
stripe. You can customize uh how the
form functions and the styling and
stuff. That's all powered by the uh
payment elements API. All that code is
built into instrumental commerce. A
combination of of a stimulus controller
with all the JavaScript involved and
some Rails controllers to make all this
stuff happen. Okay. Okay. So, we're
going to go ahead and put in a uh a test
uh credit card, the the classic 4242. My
my fingers have really remembered that
that pattern there from testing it so
many times. Okay. So, uh I've put in my
my billing information. We're going to
click the button. It's going to, you
know, go into this processing state
where we see the loading spinner. Um
now, it did pop up this uh email
notification which was sent to like me,
the the admin, right? the the admin of
the application. So the this is to you
know tell you as the product owner that
hey there's a a new uh purchase of a new
subscription. Great. Now what the
customer sees right after checkout is
they get redirected into this success
page. And of course you can customize
this. You can redirect the the user
wherever you want. All of the billing
code is right there in your Rails app.
So you can uh manage all of this. So
we're still here in the customer's
perspective here. So, the customer can
go into their settings, they can go into
billing, and now the customer sees their
own billing portal where they have all
of the details of what's happening with
their subscription. You know, which plan
they're on. Um, which payment method
they've used. They can even, you know,
change or add additional payment methods
here. Um, they can see when their next
billing date is. And, um, in this case,
it's a trial, but if they had, uh, if
they had already made some payments,
then they would see a list of their
payments history. So, you know, standard
stuff, but this kind of stuff takes a
while to actually build out in each
individual application. So, that's why I
built instrumental commerce as part of
instrumental components uh so that I can
just pop all this stuff right into my
app and I can then get into building the
actual features in my in my app. So,
we're going to get into the building
phase uh here in just a second, but a
couple more details here in this demo.
So, again, I'm the customer here. Um so,
if I want to, I can go to cancel my
subscription. That's going to take me to
a form where I can fill out a a reason
why I want to cancel. That's going to
send to the admin. Um I'll say never
mind on that for now. Um I can also go
into my um plan and I can change my
plan. So this takes me back to the to
the plans page, but this time it's a
little bit more dynamic because it it
knows that I am currently subscribed to
the starter plan. If I switch to the
yearly plan, you'll notice that this
button text now says switch to yearly.
So again, it's it's sort of like some
smart logic on this button. Um, so it
knows like I'm I'm still on the starter
plan, but I can just change to yearly or
I can upgrade up to the uh the the pro
plan. Now I'm going to go back into the
admin dashboard again. The the whole
admin component, this this whole backend
dashboard in my app, that's another
component included in instrumental
components. And back here is where where
you as the application owner can manage
um your whole commerce system starting
from your products starter and pro. And
then inside of these we have you know
prices and then you can also manage the
plans and even manage all the individual
benefits you know shown to the user here
in in these uh in these plans. So all of
this is manageable from within the
commerce section of your admin. And down
here is where you can actually uh see
the activity from your customers like
the list of purchases uh the individual
payments and then you can even see um
your active and triing and all the
different status of your subscriptions.
Then you can you know inspect each one
and you can uh get into uh the account
that owns the subscription and the
users. All that information is here for
you um in your admin dashboard. So,
that's a quick demo overview of what you
get after it's all implemented into your
Rails app. Now, let's tear it all down
and I'm going to show you how we can
actually build all of this in just a few
commands in just a few minutes. I'll
even show you a bit more like the
Dunning system and the cancellation
flows and uh and how you can test it all
uh in your local environment. All right,
let's get into it. All right, so we're
in a totally new project here, Fresh
Rails app. Now, off camerara, I did do a
couple of things to sort of lay some
groundwork. I installed the instrumental
components gem. I also installed a
couple of components like the
authentication component, the teams
component, and the admin component. Now,
I have another video covering the
installation and initial setup of of
instrumental components. You can watch
that. That'll catch you up to that
point. But now, we're at the point of
actually installing the instrumental
commerce component. So before I actually
do that, let's just uh run the server uh
just to show you where we're at with our
project so far. So again, we have the
authentication uh component all set up.
We have the teams component which sets
up accounts and everything. So I'm going
to start by just creating my uh user
account as the admin. I'll use our uh
registration form to create my own uh
user account for my my application here.
Now I want to get to my admin, but I
don't see it here. So, this is a feature
of our admin component. I'm going to
open up the the database. I like to use
table plus for that. I have a shortcut
to open that. So, I'm going to go into
my user that I just created and I'm
going to turn the admin flag to true.
And I'll save that. Refresh the app. And
now I see the admin link here. Okay. So,
that takes me into the admin dashboard.
You'll notice that we don't yet have
commerce here because I have not
actually installed the commerce
component yet. So, let's do that now.
I'm going to go into the project and
we're going to do rails g instrumental
commerce. I'm going to use the fast flag
because this is a a very big component.
There's going to be a lot of stuff to
install. So, let's just uh get through
this uh much faster. Do that. So, as
always with instrumental components,
it's going to start with giving us sort
of an overview or a preview of what it's
about to install. We've got the commerce
component plus a couple of uh additional
components like our uh panels component,
copy to clipboard, our drag and drop
reorder, that FAQ component that that
you saw during the demo. Those are going
to be used in different parts of the uh
commerce component, plus these
additional components which my project
already has installed. Those were from
the uh the previous installations. All
right, so um that all looks good. I'm
going to hit return to proceed with the
whole process. And uh as you can see I
could you know I I could see everything
that was installed here but at the very
end um actually it's it's still going so
it's just going to take a minute to
finish up. Okay. So now it is finished
and here is the recap of what was
installed. So
um uh the commerce component has been
installed. 165 files have been added
into our project. As you can see we've
got a whole bunch of uh controllers. Um,
we've got some new models. We've got a
whole lot of, uh, views and ERB
partials. Um, uh, let's see. We've got
some mailers that that we've added. Uh,
you know, different controllers and
views for the admin panels and the
userfacing stuff. Um, so yeah, there's a
lot there. We can, uh, we can kind of
dig into the codebase as we get into it.
We did insert uh some some things into
some existing files. We added a whole
bunch of migrations. We'll need to run
those. We added a couple of gems, of
course, the Stripe gem, uh, because this
is a direct Stripe integration. We have
the positioning gem for some reordering
stuff. We added a whole bunch to our
routes file. Um, all right. So, that's
all good. Let's go ahead and uh we'll do
bundle and we will run those migrations.
Oops. I always have a hard time talking
and typing at the same time.
Okay, let's restart our server. I have a
shortcut for
that. And now we see commerce down here.
Now, before we can start adding products
and prices and everything, we actually
have to set up Stripe and the connection
between Stripe and our application. So,
so there's a couple more uh setup tasks
that we'll need to do. Now, you can
refer to the instrumental components
docs. Currently, I have that here. Um,
but by the time you watch this, it'll
probably be up in a full doc site, but
all the same information will be there.
So, we're going to have to add the uh
Stripe API keys into our Rails
credentials. So, the structure of it is
here. So, you can grab that. We will
open up the Rails credentials. Now, you
know, every Rails project has a slightly
different way of of doing this. I have a
shortcut for uh editing my Rails
credentials. So, we have the structure
in there, and now we have to actually
add our publishable key and secret key.
We'll add those first. So, I'm going to
go into my Stripe account, and I'm
currently in test mode. I'll go into
developers. I'll go to, uh, API
keys, and we'll grab the publishable
key and the secret
key. Okay. So, uh, those two are all
set. Now, of course, in production,
you'll want to be in live mode. Now,
since I'm working in my local
development environment and this Stripe
integration is going to depend on Stripe
sending web hooks and my application
receiving those web hooks and listening
to those web hooks like when payments
are successful or when a subscription
has cancelled or when a subscription is
updated and things like that. Um, we
need to set up that that local
connection. So, Stripe has a really nice
way of handling this. So, first we're
going to need to make sure that we have
the Stripe CLI uh installed. And you can
get a uh a link to that here in the
docs. Um that's on Stripe's website. Get
that installed on your system. And then
you'll be able to do we'll do uh Stripe
login. Hit return. Sure that you are
connecting to the correct Stripe
account. You'll see this word here that
should match um you know the word that
you see in
here. Okay. So now I have uh
authenticated the correct Stripe
account. And
then then you can go into the docs and
grab this line. You'll want to run
stripe listen forward to localhost
3000/stripe/webhook.
Now we have a an active listener in this
uh terminal tab listening for the web
hooks that are going to be coming from
the Stripe test mode environment. Now we
need to grab this web hook signing
secret and we need to add that to our
credentials right
here. I will save and then I'll close
the credentials. And as you can see
we've we've saved those credentials. So
that's all set. One more step here.
You'll go into stripe.rb. So the
commerce component added this file to um
config initializers stripe.rb. Just
uncomment the line in there so that
we're calling on the uh the stripe
secret key from there. Okay, let's go
back into our first terminal tab. We
will stop the server and we'll um
restart it. All right, so now now that
we have the connection all set up, we
need to start actually adding in our
products and prices and plans and all
that. Um, so first let's go over to the
Stripe side. Um, and I'll show you how
I've organized things inside my Stripe
account. So in this case, very similar
to the demo that I just showed you
earlier, we're going to have um, two
products. Like Stripe calls these
products and so uh, instrumental
commerce also calls these products. I I
try to keep the naming, you know, as
consistent as possible, right? So we
have two products. Again, what you saw
earlier, the the pricing page, one is
going to be the starter plan, the other
is the pro plan. Those are products in
Stripe. And then if we open up the uh
the starter product, inside of that, we
have prices. These are prices in uh
Stripe, I've got $29 a month or 2.88 per
year. I chose 288 because when you
divide that by 12, it makes a nice
number for 24 a month, but sort of to
promote it that way. We'll get into that
in just a second. All right. So, if I
back out um the pro plan, uh it has this
old price that I'm not using anymore,
but we've got 79 and then 7.80 per
year. Okay. So, first thing is we want
to create the first product. That's
starter. So, I'm going to go into that
product in Stripe and we're going to
grab that product ID that starts with
prod and let's set that up in our
application. So, we're going to go to
new product. We're going to call that
starter. It'll be the, you know, named
the same way. We'll go into product
details. It generated a slug
automatically and that that looks good.
Of course, we can customize it if we
want to. Um, and we're going to Oops,
not that. We want
to put that product ID in as the Stripe
product ID here. We'll leave the rest of
this blank. We can use that later when
we like present the product um on the on
the front end. That's all we need in
terms of like the the product details.
Now we'll go into the price. By the way,
this whole component, this is the panels
component that this comes with um
instrumental components. So, you know,
all these elements pull in other UI
components that come with instrumental.
Okay. So, uh we're editing the starter
product. We're going to go into its
prices and we're going to add a price.
Just like we have two prices here, we
need to create the two prices in our
application. So, we'll do um starter
monthly. Now, the amount in Stripe,
that's $29 a month. We need to actually
enter that in cents. So, 2900
um that's actually
$29. And then we need to put in the
Stripe price ID. So if we go into this
price, that'll be a price ID that starts
with price underscore. You'll copy that,
drop that in there. All right. So this
is a monthly recurring price. So you'll
want to check the box to say that this
is recurring and this is a monthly plan.
So it recurs every month. Let's give
this a trial. We'll give it a 7-day
trial and we will create that price.
Cool. Now we need to create the other
one. This is the annual price. So, we'll
do um starter annual. And that price, if
I back out, that's 288 per year. Let's
go into that. We're going to need to get
that price ID as well. So, that's 280.
Oops. 288 0. And then that price ID is
that one. That one is also recurring.
This one recurs every year. Actually,
you know what? I'm going to actually set
this to uh zero days so that I can show
you both ways where you're selling a
subscription with a trial or sometimes
you might be selling subscriptions where
customers pay on day one. So I'm going
to set this one to uh zero day trial in
ter in other words like no trial. The
billing code that we have in our
controllers and everything for
instrumental commerce is set up to
handle both
scenarios. Let's create that.
I'm going to pause it here and I'm going
to create the second product pro. I'm
going to follow all the same things. I
just don't want to waste time on the
video here. So, I'll just pause. Okay.
So, now I have my two products, starter
and pro. If I go into pro, you know, I
have the product ID and I've got my two
prices for the pro plan, just like I had
them uh for the starter plan. Now, let's
see how we're doing on the front end so
far. If I open up an incognito
window, we'll go to
uh localhost plans. And so that's where
we're going to display our plans. You
actually see no plans available. Even
though we've added products and prices,
we haven't actually added the visible
plans in the pricing table yet. So those
are those are managed separately in
instrumental commerce. Um it just gives
you more control over the presentation.
So, so far all we've added is the actual
underlying products and prices. And now
we're going to set up the visual plans
that a user can choose from. So, we're
going to go into our plan section and
we're going to add our first plan.
Again, this might feel a little bit
redundant, but it actually gives you
more control and customization over
exactly what the user is going to see.
So, um this is just an internal name
first. We'll do uh
starter and uh and it'll actually be the
same as what what we show on the front
end. It'll be called starter. That's
going to be like that that blue uh label
shown at the top. And then we have a
price A and price B. So remember the
monthly and yearly toggles on the uh on
the pricing plans. That's how that's
what we sort of call the price A and
price B. So this is the the starter
plan. So, we're going to select the
monthly price for starter monthly.
That'll be our price A. And we will
select starter annual. That'll be the
price B for the starter plan. So, let's
actually back out. And I'm going to do
the same for the pro
plan. We'll call it pro. And that will
also display pro as the name. Now, in
this case, we're going to select the
pro- monthly price as price A and the
pro- annual price as price B. So, let's
create that. Let's refresh our plans
page. And there we go. So, now we see
two plans shown on the public plans
page. Since we did set both a uh a
monthly and annual price, we are seeing
the toggle here. And what this toggle is
actually doing under the hood, and we
have a whole stimulus.js controller that
that manages all of this for you, is
it's actually toggling just the price
piece, and it's toggling the URL that
these uh buttons point to. So, if I were
to click, you know, purchase Pro, and
we're currently on the yearly plan. If I
click that, it's going to take me into
the checkout flow, and I'm purchasing
the yearly plan for Pro. If I go back
and if I go to monthly, it's going to be
it's going to actually take me into
purchase the monthly plan. And by the
way, let's say I want to actually show
the starter plan first, which I actually
do. Um, I'm going to go back into my uh
plans page. And these are drag and drop,
so you can reorder these. So I'm going
to go like
this. And so now starter is shown first.
And if I refresh this. So now we have
the starter plan showing first and then
the pro plan on the right. Down here we
have the FAQ and that's all um in your
codebase. So you can go to plans. That's
the uh the partial that's managing most
of this content. And then in here you
have our uh you have the plans FAQ and
then you can manage and these this uses
our uh FAQ um component and you can
manage each question and the answer and
everything. you know, you can fill out
the rest of this page if you want to.
All right, so our planage is not quite
set yet. As as you can see, we're
currently missing those benefits. So,
let's get those filled
in. I'm going to go into the starter
plan and let's go down to benefits. And
so, now we can add benefits to the plan.
I'm going to add the first benefit
first. The first one is sort of like an
internal name. and then the benefits
text. That's the text that you see right
next to the checkbox. And then if you
want to have a tool tip next to it, you
can fill this in with some information
there. So, I'm going to create that.
Let's add a couple more benefits. I'm
going to pause the video here. Okay. So,
I've added five benefits and let's take
a look at our plans page. And so, now I
can see we have five benefits shown for
the starter plan. Notice how if I toggle
between monthly and yearly, these these
things don't change because it's the
same plan either way. So when we do that
toggle, only the price and button URL
change. All right. So now let's add
these benefits to the pro plan, but I
don't want to actually like dup I don't
want to create the benefits in two
different places. So the commerce system
is set up so that you can reuse the same
benefits on multiple plans. It makes it
really easy. So, let's go to um my other
plan, the pro plan. I'll go into
benefits and I can add a benefit. Now,
instead instead of creating a new one, I
can just add unlimited projects and I
can add unlimited
tasks. Actually, the five documents
that'll be different on the pro plan.
So, in this case, I will create a
different one. We'll do
unlimited and the others will be the
same. Okay, so that's all set. Now, I do
want to fix up the order here. And so,
these benefits are drag and drop as
well. So, I can move these around. We
want to have uh projects
first. Okay, good. So, let's take a look
at this again. And so, now we have all
of our benefits laid out exactly the way
that we want them. Great. Next, let's
talk about coupons. First, I'll show you
a quick demo. I'm looking at the plans
page, but if we were to promote this
with a special URL just by adding the
param coupon equals test code and we'll
just pretend that test code is an actual
promotional code that we've um set up in
Stripe, which I actually did. I'm going
to um reload this page. So now you can
see it dynamically detected the
existence of this coupon code in the
URL. It pinged Stripe's API to see is
this a valid coupon code? If it is, then
it's going to come back and it's
actually going to dynamically adjust the
price, crossing these out, showing the
the discounted price for, you know, each
plan. It's doing all that dynamically.
It's it's using a, you know, it's
hitting the API. It's doing that with
some uh
stimulusJS built into instrumental
commerce. U now we're seeing that here
on the plans page. And if I were to
proceed to purchasing the starter plan,
if I click that, now we're in the
checkout flow. And you can see that the
coupon was passed along and the coupon
is shown in the price details here. We
cross out the the regular price and
we're showing the discounted price. And
you can even see this detail here where
instead of it saying per year, this one
says first year. And that was customized
by me. I'm going to show you exactly how
to do that in just a second. Um, all of
this text here is customizable. And then
if I, um, you know, proceed through the
checkout emails
here. So now we're in the actual, uh,
payment collection. And again, the
coupon was passed along into this step.
We still see it here. And now we see the
coupon code down here. It's prefilled
with the coupon that's in the URL. And
if I were to just type something else in
there and make it like an invalid
coupon, it'll recheck and it'll show
that it's invalid. And then this resets
to the uh to the correct price. Now, if
I edit it again and make it a correct
coupon, it revalidates after the key up
event and it'll show me the the correct
um coupon
there. Now, sometimes you just want to
show the coupon field without prefilling
it with a valid coupon. And to do that,
all you need to do is change the coupon
param to coupon equals
true. And so now we see the payment form
with an empty coupon field that the user
could put in a coupon code if they have
one. Now the reason why this is actually
hidden by default if we get rid of the
coupon parameter al
together we actually hide the coupon
field. And that is an optimization when
it comes to e-commerce and checkout
because you don't want to show users
that there is a coupon field if they
don't have one. Um, you know, then they
might go hunting for a coupon. They
might abandon their checkout and of
course we don't want that. So I always
find that it's helpful to be able to
promote direct URLs whether it's from a
email campaign or an advertising
campaign or a social media. You can
point that to your checkout to promote a
special sale only to certain people who
might be aware that there's a coupon or
that or you might be giving them a
coupon. But other public visitors should
be able to just go through the checkout
without any discount. Now, in this case,
um you know, we have the coupon applied.
So, I'm going to go ahead and uh and
complete the the checkout
here. So, for the customer, they reached
the success page. And for me as the app
owner, I received my notification, my
mailer, that there has been a new
purchase, a new subscription. And in
this case, it's showing me a different
payment for today, which is different
from what the product price will be
because, you know, they got half off on
the first year. And if we look at the
customer in
Stripe, you know, since I refreshed it a
few times, you see these incompletes.
Those are going to be cleared out by
Stripe. Um, but here is the active
subscription that we just
created. And you can see down here that
the first payment was discounted thanks
to the coupon. Now, let's sort of
backtrack a little bit. We're going to
do this whole process again. And I'm
going to show you how you can actually
customize your coupon. So, if I go into
um the plans page again, we're going to
apply that same coupon. Coupon equals
test code. Oops, spelled it wrong. As
you can see, I spelled it wrong there.
So that that is an invalid coupon and it
did not show a discount. So it's only
showing it if it actually pulls a valid
coupon from the Stripe API. Test code.
Okay. So now we have the valid code
applied. And if I go back into the
checkout flow. So let me show you how
this is actually wired up. So if I go
into my Stripe account, if I go into
product catalog, go to
coupons, here is my test coupon. So, I
created this test
coupon and then inside the test coupon,
you'll have promotion codes. Stripe
calls them promotion codes. That's what
we're using here. This is the actual
code. In this case, it says test code.
That's the thing that the customer sees.
Um, so we will go into that. And now we
have some metadata. So, I'm going to
edit this and um and just delete these
metadata items because it would be uh
blank by default. There there would be
no metadata. So if you so you you'll
create a coupon and you'll create the
promotional codes for that coupon and
then inside the metadata for the
promotion code if you leave the metadata
blank that's totally fine. But here's
what's going to happen on the front end.
If I refresh this
um first we only show this message here.
That's like the default fallback uh
success message. It just says coupon
applied. And the price here, we have our
own logic built into the stimulus.js
uh controller that handles displaying
the coupon code here. So, it's going to
actually calculate the discount, in this
case, 50% off of the 288. And it's going
to display that with the same text
that's shown here. But that's a little
bit misleading in this case because this
particular coupon is set up to only give
you 50% off in your first year, right?
And so that so we have metadata to
customize that. So first let's customize
this text. I'm going to go back into my
Stripe uh coupon and then inside the
promotional code in that metadata I'm
going to do success message. And by the
way, all of this is documented in the
documents for instrumental commerce.
You'll find that here. So success
message is the first one that we want to
set. And we're going to say um you're in
instead of coupon applied. If I refresh
this now, it says you're in. We want to
add one more sentence uh description
down below. So I'm going to um add
another metadata item. And this one is
going to be our success
description. Thanks for being awesome.
We'll add that. I'll refresh. And so now
we see that description down here. All
right. So now let's handle this and make
it more accurate to what the um what the
coupon actually
does. So for that we are going to want
to use the custom append text. We could
use the custom price text. And what that
would do is um it would be a totally
customized text like all the way through
if you want to have like a very specific
dollar amount or some other uh message
that you want to show there in terms of
the the replaced price. Instead of that,
we're not going to use that one in this
case. We're we're still going to use our
own logic for calculating the amount
because the amount would be different
depending on which plan you're on. But
we do want to calculate the text that
come the text that is appended after it.
So that is why we have the custom append
text metadata. I'm going to add that.
We're going to add the third item here.
And instead of per year, we're going to
write first
year. And I'll refresh that. And so now
it's displaying how we exactly want it.
We're giving the customer a very
accurate view in terms of what this
discount that they're getting for the
first year. It's not every year. So, all
of these little details are really
important because it gives customers
confidence when they're going through
the checkout flow. And that of course
leads to higher conversions, more
purchases, more revenue, better
business. These things are really
important. It's a lot of technical
details on the back end and in our
codebase, and you can dig into them in
your into your project. But when it
comes to actually running a SAS
business, these kind of details really,
really matter. Let's move on now to the
Dunning system. So, first we're going to
go back. I'll just start a a new
incognito session here. And what I'm
going to demonstrate here is subscribing
with a credit card that will fail when
the subscription starts to renew or, you
know, start to charge the card. And then
I'm going to show you how instrumental
commerce handles that and gets the
customer to resolve their own
subscription so that we don't lose out
on that revenue. All right. So, I'm
going to subscribe now to the starter
plan that's on a trial. I'm going to
choose that and I can see the trial
information here. I'm going to um you
know create a new
account. All right. So, now I'm in the
payment details. Now, in order to test
this out and demonstrate it, you'll want
to use a very specific Stripe test
credit card. So, if you open up Google
and just go to um Stripe test cards,
you'll find this page. So, this is a
page where Stripe gives you, you know, a
whole list of test credit cards. Um so,
you can test all these different
scenarios. These are all the success
cases. Um, but then if you scroll down,
if you go down to declined payments, you
can test here what would happen if you
enter a credit card. That that should
generate a decline. But down here, this
is a very specific one. It's going to
decline after attaching. That means that
when we initially attach it, when we
initially use this credit card in the
checkout flow, it's going to be
successful here. It's not actually
charging because this is going to start
a free trial. It's going to create
what's known as a setup intent in the
Stripe API and um it's going to be
successful here. So, I'm going to put
this in. But then later when when we go
into the future and we charge the the
the first subscription charge for this
um that is going to fail. So, that's
what this um specific card, the 0341
card is going to do. So, I'm just going
to um fill out this checkout here. I'm
going to start my 7-day trial. By the
way, this button, the the text is
dynamic. So, if you're selling a trial,
then it'll show the the trial here. If
you're just selling it with no trial,
it'll say purchase uh the subscription.
All right. So, let's go ahead and
process that. Now, the customer is like
in their free trial. Um they haven't yet
been uh build for the first time, but
when they do, that's going to fail. So,
how do we actually simulate that? Well,
Stripe has a really cool feature to
simulate the passage of time, and we're
going to use that right now. Go into
Stripe, and here is that most recent
customer. You can see this customer is
on the starter plan. It It's on a free
trial. It hasn't been built yet. And the
payment methods is this
0341. And that is expected to fail when
we get up to the first uh charge, which
should be 7 days from now because it's a
7-day free trial. So to simulate this,
we go into the subscription itself. And
here is this really cool feature with
Stripe. You can run a simulation, right?
And so what's going to happen here is
we're going to actually like take like a
like a like a time capsule into the
future. And I want to go one week into
the future. Actually, we'll do one week
plus one day. So this is eight days into
the future. The the first charge is
going to be seven days from now. So,
we're going to fast forward through, you
know, past the day where they're
supposed to be charged, and that charge
is going to fail. Now, when I do this
and we advance the time, once we get up
to that seventh day and charge, it's
going to fail, and then it should send
uh an email to the customer, and we're
going to see that. All right. So, let's
go ahead and advance the
time, and you'll see this sort of play
out right here. And you can even look at
your logs and you can see um that. Okay.
So now using letter opener gem to test
our mailers. Now we're seeing the actual
mailer that is sent to the customer. So
the customer received this this email.
Um you can customize the the content of
this mailer. Of course we do have some
code in here to automatically detect
your primary color in your Tailwind
colors. I'm going to use that to render
this button in the uh the email that a
customer receives. Now, from a business
standpoint, one of my um core goals here
is to make this as frictionless as
possible. Make it really easy for a
customer to resolve their own
subscription that is now past due. And
before I get into that, let's just take
a look at the subscription. As you can
see, now the subscription is past due
because the payment
failed. So, we're going to go back into
this malor
and and let's actually close out of this
incognito window so that um we are
simulating the case where the customer
received the email but the customer is
not even logged in to our application.
Again, we don't want to add friction. We
just want to have the customer click
this button and be able to resolve
straight away. So, I'm going to click
the button. We are going to open it up
in an incognito tab just to sort of like
demonstrate this. But it it's the same
as if the customer just clicked the
button in the email that they received.
And then we take them to this very
clean, simple resolution page where they
could just enter a new uh successful
credit card to uh to to pay for their
card. We also give them uh a a simple
link here to use uh their existing
credit card. So that would be helpful if
they've already called their bank,
they've they've resolved whatever issue
it is. So, they could click that and
then they can just retry their current
card. Very easy. Or if they just
actually need to change to a new uh
payment method, then they can click this
and it's going to load the new uh
payment form. All right. So, let's go
ahead and have the customer put in a
successful card this time and they will
pay. And actually, we need to uh fix the
little currency symbol there. We'll get
that fixed. We're going to process that.
and all set. Uh I actually it's going to
ask me to log in because I wasn't
actually fully logged in. We did sort of
uh identify the customer using a special
resolution token uh from the button
here. But if we go back into Stripe and
we refresh this
subscription now, we see the
subscription is active again. Pew. You
know, we we've uh we've we've resolved
that subscription. actually the customer
resolved it on their own. So this is a
really important piece of any SAS
business. You don't want this
subscription revenue sort of like
leaking out of out of the out of the
business,
right? Okay. So I'm going to actually
log in as the customer
again and I'm back into my application
and I can go into my uh settings and I
see the
billing. So the last piece that I want
to show you here is the uh cancellation
flow. So, if I'm the customer and I want
to actually cancel my account, I can go
to cancel my subscription and that's
going to take me to this form. And
again, this is one of those business
things that I think is really important.
We always want to know what are the top
reasons for the churn that's happening
in our subscription business. You know,
why do customers want to cancel? You can
get a lot of really good insights from
this form. So, we're going to ask the
customer um to give us a reason. you
know, it wasn't a good fit because what,
you know, okay, so I'm going to go ahead
and cancel my subscription if I click
this. So, this is the mailer that is
again sent to the admin, you know, you
as as the product owner. And this, you
know, informs you that a subscription
has been cancelled and it gives you um
the reason that the customer typed in.
And by the way, the reply to is also
pointing to the customer's email
address, which is a really good thing
because you can just reply to this email
and get into an exchange with the
customer and have a discussion and try
to learn more from your customers so you
can see why they're cancelling, how you
can make your product better, and reduce
your turn rate. Now, on the customer's
end, they're taken back into their uh
subscription overview. Um, it will
actually schedule the cancellation for
the end of the billing cycle. So, it's
not going to um schedule it immediately
because they did pay for the current
month. So, as you can see, the status
here says cancellation scheduled. And if
we look at Stripe, we uh refresh the
subscription. It's still active as of
today, but it is scheduled to cancel on
June 24th. And if the customer just
wants to resume their subscription, all
they need to do is click this button.
And just like that, I resumed my
subscription as the customer. And we're
back to uh active status. If I refresh
the subscription in Stripe, it's back to
active. It's not going to cancel. So all
these little details, all these little
interactions, they are handled between
your application and Stripe. You know,
again, like these are really important
details because each individual one um
might seem small on its own, but it all
adds up to a healthy, robust SAS
business. You know, you need um you need
to have customers being able to
subscribe and check out, of course, but
you also need to have customers changing
their plans and resolving their past due
plans and cancelling and then resuming
their plans. I mean, one of the most
interesting things about my SAS business
is that customers cancel and then they
often come back and they resume their
plan like four, six, eight months down
the line. So, um you always want to have
these details handled.
Now, I know I didn't actually show you
too much of the um of the actual code,
but um you all of this now resides in
your Rails project. So, one thing that
you'll you'll see is that all of the
instrumental commerce component is
actually underneath the namespace
commerce. The checkout controller is
where a lot of the action happens, you
know, from like the the registration
flow into um initiating the uh the
payment intent that you know that's how
it connects to uh to the Stripe API and
then we also process the checkout.
There's sort of like a like a like a
handshake that happens that goes back
and forth between the Stripe API and our
application. All of that is handled. Um
we also uh validate the coupon in here.
The other thing the other important uh
file in this whole system is the
checkout controller JS. This is the uh
stimulus controller that we've built
built right into that uh that whole
transaction that that happens between
Stripe and um and the checkout. And all
of this is also incorporated in with the
uh like the payment method. So the
payment methods controller uh handles um
adding and removing payment method
methods, changing a default payment
method. I've got a a coupon controller.
So inside the JavaScript folder inside
controllers um you know your stimulus
controllers are all in here, but the
commerce specific stimulus controllers
are in their own uh name space. And then
same thing in the admin. So um the admin
uh component gives you an admin
namespace and then within there we have
uh some commerce specific controllers
and these that's what's handling you
know the uh the admin commerce backend
here where we're managing our uh
products and prices and and all this
kind of stuff. So as you saw in this
video there is a lot there. It's all
intertwined. All the logic is right
there in your project for you to uh dig
into. I tried to you know uh comment it
as much as possible and of course um
it's all documented in the docs which
are continuing to evolve. So by the time
you watch this uh video and get into the
docs there will be even more there. So
um all that is included in instrumental
components and if you have any questions
you can ask me or you can join our uh
customers group and if you want more of
a highle overview of instrumental
components you can see the other video
that I just recorded there which
installed the base component system the
admin system the authentication system
the team system there's so much
more. All right thank you for watching.
Uh this was a long one but it's all
there. See you.